Guide to the Sylvester Manor Archive 1649-1996 MSS 208
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sylvester Manor Archive
1649-1996
MSS 208
Fales Library and Special Collections
88.37 linear feet (159 boxes)
Sylvester Manor is the home of the original European settlers on Shelter Island in eastern Long Island, New York, created in 1652 with the arrival of Nathaniel and Grissell Sylvester. For over 350 years and continuing to this day, the Manor has remained with descendents of the original Sylvesters, and the Sylvester Manor Archive contains documents dating from its European settlement to the late-20th century. The earliest documents provide evidence of an operational northern provisioning plantation involved in the Atlantic trade of the 17th century, while later portions of the collection document the lives of several notable descendents including Ezra L’Hommedieu, an attorney and politician from the American Revolutionary Era, Samuel Smith Gardiner, an attorney from a prominent family of eastern Long Island, and Eben Norton Horsford, a scientist at the forefront of the development of American food science and chemistry and a successful entrepreneur.
Fiske, Andrew, 1912-1992
Gardiner, Samuel Smith, 1789-1859
Horsford, Eben Norton, 1818-1893
L'Hommedieu, Ezra, 1734-1811
Sylvester, Nathaniel, 1610-1680
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Some oversize and artifact materials have not been processed and are currently unavailable to researchers.
Due to preservation concerns, some documents may be unavailable to researchers. These documents are noted in the finding aid.
Related Archival Material
Dering Papers, Shelter Island Historical Society, Shelter Island, New York.
Horsford Family Papers, Institute Archives and Special Collections, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York.
Rumford Chemical Company Records MSS 13 SG 2, Rhode Island Historical Society, Providence, Rhode Island.
Arrangement note
Materials are divided into record groups by their general family affiliation (Sylvester, L’Hommedieu, Gardiner, Horsford, and Fiske) and subdivided into series consisting of individuals’ papers. Women that crossed family divisions, such as Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu (Gardiner), and Phoebe Gardiner (Horsford), were included in their married family because most records date from after marriage. Sub-series are identified by the document or material types. Materials are arranged depending on the record type; correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically, most other materials are arranged chronologically except where noted.
RECORD GROUP I: Sylvester and Early Familes
Series A: Sylvester Family
Series B: Brinley Family
Series C: Lloyd Family
RECORD GROUP II: L'Hommedieu Family
Series A: Benjamin L'Hommedieu II
Subseries 1: Legal and Financial Materials
Series B: Ezra L'Hommedieu
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Financial and Accounting Materials
Subseries 3: Legal Documents
Subseries 4: Court and Legal Case Documents
Subseries 5: Published Materials
Subseries 6: US Government Documents and Reports
Subseries 7: New York Government Documents and Reports
Subseries 8: Upstate New York Land Materials
Subseries 9: Miscellaneous Materials
Series C: Mary Catherine Havens L'Hommedieu
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Legal and Financial Materials
Series D: Thomas Lester
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Series E: Sylvester Dering
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Series F: Oversize Materials
RECORD GROUP III: Gardiner Family
Series A: Samuel S. Gardiner
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Financial Materials
Subseries 3: Account Books and Ledgers
Subseries 4: Legal Papers
Subseries 5: Government and Political Publications
Subseries 6: Printed Materials
Subseries 7: Miscellaneous Manuscripts
Series B: Mary Catherine L'Hommedieu Gardiner
Subseries 1: Correspondence and Additional Materials
Series C: Oversize Materials
RECORD GROUP IV: Horsford Family
Series A: Eben N. Horsford
Subseries 1a: Family and General Correspondence
Subseries 1b: Wellesley Correspondence
Subseries 1c: Rumford Chemical Works
Subseries 1d: Civil War/Army Ration
Subseries 2: Financial Documents
Subseries 3: Shelter Island and Cambridge Materials
Subseries 4: Personal Journals and Notebooks
Subseries 5: Scientific Papers
Subseries 6: Business and Patent Papers
Subseries 7: University, Associations and Club Materials
Subseries 8: Norumbega/Northmen Materials
Subseries 9: Travel and Event Materials
Subseries 10: Newspapers and Magazines
Subseries 11: Poetry and Miscellaneous Materials
Subseries 12: Maps
Series B: Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner (Horsford)
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Manuscript
Series C: Phoebe D. Gardiner (Horsford)
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Legal and Financial Documents
Subseries 3: Manuscripts
Series D: Lilian Horsford (Farlow)
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Manuscripts and Other Materials
Subseries 3: Visual Materials
Series E: Mary Catherine (Kate) Horsford
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Manuscripts
Subseries 3: Visual Materials
Series F: Gertrude Horsford (Fiske)
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Series G: Mary Gardiner Horsford (Curtis)
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Series H: Cornelia C.F. Horsford
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: Archaeology and Research Materials
Subseries 3: Financial and Sylvester Manor Materials
Subseries 4: Geneology and Local History
Subseries 5: Manuscripts and Other Materials
Subseries 6: Visual Materials
Subseries 7: Plans and Blueprints
Series I: General Horsford Materials
Subseries 1: Correspondence
Subseries 2: History/Genealogy Materials
Subseries 3: Financial and Sylvester Manor Materials
Subseries 4: Memorial Programs
Subseries 5: Newspaper, Clippings, and Scrapbooks
Subseries 6: Poetry and Manuscripts
Subseries 7: Gardening Materials
Subseries 8: Visual Materials
Series J: Oversize Materials
RECORD GROUP V: Fiske Family
Series A: Correspondence and General Papers
Series B: Plans, Blueprints and Other Items
Series C: Oversize Materials
RECORD GROUP VI: Photographic Material
Series A: People and Portraits
Series B: Sylvester Manor, 27 Craigie Street House, Etc
Series C: Miscellaneous
Series D: Photo Albums
Series E: Glass Plate Negatives and Slides
RECORD GROUP VII: Artifacts
Scope and Content note
The Sylvester Manor Archive contains correspondence, financial records, manuscripts, photographs, artworks, and realia from the owners and related family members of the Sylvester Manor. The Archive spans more than 350 years and different portions will likely be of interest for different purposes. The earliest documents in the collection are particularly strong in early land deeds and records relating to Long Island, including deeds containing Native American signatures, notably that of Wyandanch, sachem of the Mantaukett Indians. A number of wills and ledgers relating to trade in the Atlantic world in the late 17th and early 18th century are also present. Later records are the largely the personal records of the individuals who lived at Sylvester Manor, several of whom had noteworthy careers in their respective fields. The records of three individuals comprise the bulk of the collection: Ezra L’Hommedieu, a prominent attorney and politician; Samuel Smith Gardiner, a Long Island and New York attorney; and Eben Norton Horsford, an early leader in the science of food chemistry and owner of the Rumford Chemical Works. Other significant groups of records include the early records of the Sylvester, Brinley, and Lloyd families, as well as the papers of Cornelia Horsford. A large number of photographs dating from approximately the 1870s through the 1930s document Sylvester Manor and its grounds as well as members of the Horsford and Fiske families.
Historical Note
Sylvester Manor and its grounds are located on Shelter Island, an 8,000-acre island situated between the north and south forks of eastern Long Island that was inhabited by Manhansett Indians until its purchase in 1651 by the first permanent European settlers. Nathaniel Sylvester, an Englishman born and raised in Amsterdam, and three Barbadian planters, his brother, Constant, Thomas Middleton, and Thomas Rouse, bought the property to use in the Caribbean provisioning trade. Enslaved Africans, impressed Natives, and European indentured servants raised livestock and produced timber for barrels, and food to sell in the West Indies, where most arable land was devoted to valuable sugar cane. In 1653, Nathaniel (Nathaniell in most records) Sylvester and his wife Grissell Brinley (also recorded Grizzell), married and moved to Shelter Island, creating the establishment that would later bear their family name. The property was granted royal manor status by Governor Richard Nicoll of New York Colony in 1666.
In 1752 with the death of Brinley Sylvester, the estate passed to his daughter, Mary (Nathaniel’s great-great granddaughter), and her husband Thomas Dering. The Manor remained in the Dering family for another two generations before debt forced the sale of the property. Dering records do not appear in any number in the Archive. The property was purchased from the Derings in 1827 by Samuel Smith Gardiner, a Suffolk County and New York attorney who had married into a different branch of Sylvester descendents.
Samuel Gardiner’s wife was Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu, the daughter of Ezra L’Hommedieu, a very prominent attorney, national and state political representative, Suffolk County Clerk for some twenty years, and a great-great grandson of Nathaniel Sylvester. Although Ezra L’Hommedieu never owned Sylvester Manor, the collection houses a substantial volume of his papers. The Gardiners produced three daughters, Mary L’Hommedieu Gardiner, Phoebe Dayton Gardiner (sometimes spelled Phebe, particularly in earlier records), and Frances (Fanny) Gardiner.
Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner wed Eben Norton Horsford, a professor of chemistry at Harvard University, a pioneer in food science, and founder of the Rumford Chemical Works in Providence, Rhode Island. Mary and E.N. produced four daughters, Lillian (also Lilian), Mary Katherine (Kate), Gertrude, and Mary Gardiner (Mamie). Mary died in 1855, and E.N. Horsford married her sister Phoebe two years later. Phoebe gave birth to one daughter, Cornelia Conway Fenton (referred to as Nellie in her younger years). Samuel Gardiner died in 1859, passing the Manor to Phoebe and E.N. Horsford, at which time it became a summer home, as the Horsfords were well established in Cambridge, Massachusetts. Following her mother's death in 1903, Cornelia Horsford, who never married, retained the property until her death in 1944. The property then passed to the Fiske family, a family of Boston attorneys into which Gertrude Horsford had married. Augustus Henry Fiske briefly inherited the Manor before passing the estate to his son Andrew, who held the Manor from 1949 until his death in 1992. His widow, Alice Hench Fiske, retained life interest until her death in 2006.
The original house was probably constructed soon after Nathaniel and Grissell’s arrival. Provisioning activities likely ended in 1680 at Nathaniel’s death, but farming and trading continued. After Brinley Sylvester, a successful merchant operating regionally in the New England and New York sphere, tore down the first dwelling, he constructed the current surviving house around 1735 By the time Samuel Gardiner became the owner of the manor in the early 19th century, the Manor property had been significantly reduced and much of the remaining arable land was leased to local farmers. When the Horsfords took possession they hosted members of Boston's intellectual and social elites during the summers. Some small scale farming continued. The existing gardens were formalized and expanded, and the Horsfords set up monuments and fenced enclosures including two extant graveyards, to relate their understanding in landscape features of the property's history. After her mother's death, Cornelia Horsford maintained the home as a summer residence, continuing work on the gardens and overseeing a substantial renovation to the residence by the well-known architect, Henry Bacon, in 1908.
The estate currently comprises approximately 243 acres, the manor house, and several subsidiary houses, barns and out-buildings, most of which date to the nineteenth century. Sylvester Manor remains in the possession of family descendents and is today being cultivated as an educational organic farm. In addition, nine seasons of field schools were conducted by archaeological teams from the University of Massachusetts Boston, providing further information on the original buildings and activities conducted on the site. See http://www.fiskecenter.umb.edu/excavations.htm for information on the archaeological activities.
Due to the large number of individuals whose records are included in the Archive, more detailed Biographical Notes are made at the appropriate level of the finding aid.
Sources:
Sylvester Manor Archive, MSS 208, Fales Library and Special Collections, New York University Libraries.
Thompson, Benjamin F. History of Long Island, Vol. II. Port Washington, N.Y.: Ira Friedman, Inc., 1962
Provenance
The Sylvester Manor Archive was donated to NYU by Eben Fiske Ostby; the donation was initiated by Alice (Hench) Fiske and overseen by Mac Griswold with the assistance of Melanie Martin in 2008. The materials were retrieved from the Sylvester Manor house on Shelter Island.
Separated Materials
Selected printed materials have been removed to Fales Special collections and cataloged. These items are noted in the finding aid. To see a list of cataloged items, search for "Sylvester Manor Archive" in BobCat.
Barnard, Frederick A. P., (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889; Botta, Anne C. Lynch (Anne Charlotte Lynch), 1815-1891; Brinley, Francis, 1632-1719; Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Curtis, Mary Gardiner Horsford, (Mamie), 1855-1893; Dering, Sylvester, 1758-1820; Dewey, Melvil, 1851-1931; Durant, H.F., (Henry Fowle), 1822-1881; Dyckman, William N.; Farlow, Mary Leila, (Lilian), 1848-1927; Fields, Annie, 1834-1915; Fiske, Augustus Henry, 1880-1944; Fiske, Gertrude Hubbard Horsford, b. 1852; Floyd, Nicoll, 1762-1852; Floyd, William, 1734-1821; Gardiner, David; Gardiner, Lion, 1599-1663; Gardiner, Mary Catherine L'Hommedieu, 1806-1838; Gelston, David; Grant, Ulysses S., (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Hall, James, 1811-1898; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Horsford, Cornelia Conway Fenton, 1861-1944; Horsford, Jerediah, 1791-1875; Horsford, Mary Katherine, (Kate), 1850-1927; Horsford, Phoebe Dayton Gardiner, 1826-1903; Jackson, Helen Hunt, 1830-1885; Jay, John, 1745-1829; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jewett, Sarah Orne, 1849-1909; L'Hommedieu, Benjamin, 1694-1755; L'Hommedieu, Mary Catherine Havens, 1765-1843; Lester, Thomas; Liebig, Justus, Freiherr von, 1803-1873; Lloyd, Henry, 1685-1763; Lloyd, James; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; New York (State). Legislature.; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902; Rumford Chemical Works.; Smith, John, 1752-1816; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869; Susquehannah Company.; Sylvester, Brinley, 1694-1752; Sylvester, Constant; Sylvester, Giles, 1657-1704; Sylvester, Grissell, 1635-1687; Sylvester, Nathaniel, 1610-1680; Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835; Tyler, John, 1790-1862; Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1820-1889; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Wilson, George F., (George Francis), 1818-1883; Wyandance, Sachem, ca. 1571-1659; Account books.; Accounts.; Administrative records.; Advertisements.; Agriculture and state; American literature |y 19th century.; American newspapers |z New York (State); Architectural drawings (visual works); Authors and artists.; Authors |z United States.; Authors, American |y 19th century |v Correspondence.; Book collecting.; Books and reading |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Broadsides (notices); Cabinet photographs.; Cambridge (Mass.); Chemistry |x History |y 19th century.; Contracts.; Cookery, American |x History |y 19th century.; Education and state |z United States |x History |y 19th century.; Education, Higher |z United States |x History |y 19th century; Ephemera.; Essays.; Eulogies.; Farm produce; Farmers |z New York (State); Farming; Fiction |y 19th century.; Financial records.; Fliers (printed matter); Food industry and trade |z New York (State) |z New York; Food science and technology |x History.; Food science and technology.; Gardening |x History.; Genealogy.; Governors |z New York (State).; Ground plans.; Harvard University |x History |y 19th century.; Law |z New York (State) |x History.; Law |z United States |x History.; Legal documents.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |x Colonial period.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y 17th century.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y 19th century.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century.; Long Island (N.Y.)|x History.; Manuscripts for publication.; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) |x History |y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; New York (N.Y.) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783.; New York (N.Y.) |x Social life and customs.; New York (State) |x Genealogy |v Archival resources.; New York (State) |x History |y 1775-1865.; New York (State) |x History |y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Newspapers.; North Atlantic Region |x Commerce |x History |y 17th century.; North Atlantic Region |x Commerce |x History |y 18th century.; North Atlantic Region.; North Atlantic Region|x History.; Norumbega (Extinct city); Notebooks.; Notes.; Novelists, American |y 19th century.; Official reports.; Periodicals.; Personal correspondence.; Personal papers.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Plantation life.; Poetry.; Postcards.; Printed ephemera.; Printed materials.; Proofs (printed matter); Rumford Chemical Works.; Shelter Island (N.Y.); Shelter Island (N.Y.) |x History.; Slavery |z America |x History.; Slavery |z New York (State) |z Long Island |x History.; Vikings |z North America.
- Record Group I: Sylvester, Brinley, and Lloyd Families
  Scope and Content note
  This record group contains records of the Sylvester, Brinley and Lloyd families, dating from 1649 to 1786. These documents provide evidence of an early northern provisioning plantation actively involved in the Atlantic trades and employing African slave labor, Native Americans, and early European settlers. Financial and accounting evidence of trading activities as well as a number of wills and land ownership documents of various family members provide detailed inventories of possessions during this period.
  - Series A: Sylvester Family (Oversize)
    Biographical Note
    The Sylvester Family was involved in the original purchase of Shelter Island in 1651 for the purposes of establishing a provisioning plantation for its Barbados sugar operations. Nathaniel Sylvester (1610-1680) was a member of an English merchant family that had briefly relocated to the Netherlands before moving to Barbados to manage the family’s interests in a sugar plantation. He married Grissell Brinley (1635-1687), who was the daughter of Francis Brinley, a merchant of some wealth based in Boston and Rhode Island. The couple came to live on Shelter Island in 1652 as the first Europeans to permanently settle there. The couple produced 11 children, including Giles Sylvester (1657-1704), who inherited the heart of the estate from his father, while portions were given to the four other sons (portions of the island had also been given to Constant Sylvester). The Sylvesters were sympathetic to the Quaker religion, and provided shelter to several of its followers during persecutions in other areas of New England. After Nathaniel’s death, the property was no longer affiliated with the sugar plantation in Barbados that had been operated by Nathaniel’s brother Constant. Giles Sylvester died without heir and following a legal dispute the property passed to Brinley Sylvester (1694-1752), Giles’ nephew via his brother Nathaniel II. Brinley Sylvester pursued trading and other maritime merchant activities. He married Mary Burrough and had two daughters, of which Mary Sylvester would marry Thomas Dering and later inherit the estate.
    The papers in the series contain records relating to the members of the Sylvester family and include land deeds, wills, correspondence, manorial grants for Shelter Island, and accounts and ledgers of their merchant activities. A number of land and legal documents relate to Horse Neck Island (now known as Lloyd’s Neck) on the northern shore of Long Island; this property was purchased by Nathaniel for his daughter Grissell, who was engaged to be married to Latimer Sampson, who died before they were wed. Grissell then married James Lloyd, whose papers are included in the Lloyd Family series below.
    Selected printed materials have been removed to Fales Special collections and cataloged. Please search Bobcat to locate these items.
    - Letter - Lion Gardiner to John Winthrop, 1649 April 16; Signed by Lion Gardiner. (Box 140, Folder 1)
    - Deed of Sale - Horseneck, with American Indian Signatures (Wyandanch), 1654 September 20 (Box 140, Folder 2)
    - Letter - Nathaniell Sylvester to John Winthrop, 1654 (Box 140, Folder 3)
    - Agreement Between John Richbell and Nathaniell Sylvester re Horse Neck, 1664 January 8 (Box 140, Folder 4)
    - Agreement Between John Richbell and Nathaniell Sylvester re Horse Neck [copy], 1664 January 8 (Box 140, Folder 5)
    - Horseneck Deed - Captain John Scott, John Richbell, John Leveritt, [1665] (Box 154, Folder 1)
    - Enfranchisement for Shelter Island by Richard Nicolls to Constant and Nathaniell Sylvester, 1666 May 31 (Box 140, Folder 6)
    - Agreement Between Nathaniell Sylvester and Latimer Sampson re Horse Neck, 1666 October 18 (Box 140, Folder 7)
    - Indenture - John and Ann Richbell to Nathaniell Sylvester, Thomas Hart and Latimer Sampson for Horseneck [folded], 1666 November 17 (Box 140, Folder 8)
    - Amendments to Bill of Sale of John Richbell to Thomas Hart and Latimer Sampson re Horse Neck, circa 1666 (Box 140, Folder 9)
    - Cambridge County Court Document re Estate of Samuel Andrews (Horse Neck) [copy of 1660 original document], 1667 November 28 (Box 140, Folder 10)
    - Quit Claim - Nathaniell Sylvester to Thomas Hart and Latimer Sampson for Horseneck, 1668 November 17 (Box 140, Folder 11)
    - Last Will and Testament - Latimer Sampson, 1668 (Box 140, Folder 12)
    - Letter - Samuel Bellingham to James Johnson and Oeter Oliver [copy by Nathaniell Sylvester], 1669 April 23 (Box 140, Folder 13)
    - Governor Edmund Andros Confirmation of Will of Latimer Sampson, 1675 March 1 (Box 140, Folder 14)
    - Deed - Thomas Hart to James Lloyd, Horse Neck; Assign/Grant - James Lloyd to Nathaniell Sylvester, Horse Neck, 1678 October 11 (Box 140, Folder 15)
    - Bill of Sale/Deed - Thomas Hart to James Lloyd for Horse Neck, 1678 October 7 (Box 140, Folder 16)
    - Deed of Sale - Nathaniell Sylvester to James Lloyd, for Horse Neck, 1678 November 5 (Box 140, Folder 17)
    - Deed - Estate of Nathaniell Sylvester to James Lloyd for Horse Neck, 1683 February 6 (Box 140, Folder 18)
    - Gov. Richard Nicolls charter to Nathaniel Sylvester for Horse Neck (copy on parchment), 1683/4 March 19 (Map-case Map case 4.B, Folder 4)
    - Grizzell Sylvester - Last Will and Testament, 1685 May 7 (Box 140, Folder 19)
    - Bond - Nathaniell Sylvester (II) to Isaac Arnold and James Lloyd for Slave, 1687 September 20 (Box 140, Folder 20)
    - Bill of Sale - Estate of Nathaniell Sylvester to James Lloyd, for four slaves, 1687 September 26 (Box 140, Folder 21)
    - Bond - Peter Sylvester to James Lloyd, for two slaves, 1688 September 11 (Box 140, Folder 22)
    - Description of Transactions at the Time of Seizure of Governor Andross [later copy?], 1689 April 22 (Box 140, Folder 23)